right so we're going to talk about
energy based models and it's basically a
farm arc which we can through which we
can express a lot of different learning
algorithms not the ones that are kind
simple like like we've seen in
supervised running but but the things
that are a little more sophisticated and
it sort of encompasses also a lot of
artistic methods but it's a little
simpler to understand I think then the
probably sick methods and probably sick
methods really are kind of a special
case if you want off of energy based
models and I think it's kind of
informally that's a little sort of
enlightening in the sense that it
explains a lot of things that seem very
different when when you don't get this
sort of unifying view of things so what
I'm going to talk about first applies
equally well to supervised learning what
some people call supervised running or
whatever we call self supervised running
we shall talk about a little bit today
and it's basically we're going to talk
about models that observe a set of
variables X and we're asking the model
to predict a set of variables Y and I'm
not specifying that X is an image or
whatever and Y is a is a discrete
variable like for classification Y could
be like an integral Y and X could be an
interview or X could be an image and Y a
piece of text that describes it or X
could be a sentence in one language and
Y sentence in another language
X could be an entire text and Y could be
a simplified version of that text or an
abstract so it could be anything really
I'm not kind of specifying this a Sara
Lee here but it comes from the fact that
these two issues with sort of
feed-forward models whether they are
neural nets or something else doesn't
matter a classical model precedes by you
know doing if a finite fixed number of
calculations to produce an output if you
have a multi-layer
that you know there is a fixed number of
layers even if you have a recurrent net
there is some sort of limit to how many
times you can unfold it so it's you know
basically a fixed amount of computation
but there are there are two issues for
which this is not entirely appropriate
the the the first one or two situations
the first situation is when computing
the output requires some more complex
calculation and just virtual weighted
sums and non-linearity in a kind of
finite number when the inference is
complex and the second situation is when
we are trying to train the machine to
produce not a single output but a
possible set of outputs so in the case
of classification we're actually
training a machine to produce multiple
outputs we are training it to produce a
separate score for every possible
category that we have in our you know
system ideally the system would prove we
produce the the best score for the
correct class and you know if you need a
small scores for for the other ones in
practice you know when we run the output
of a normal to soft max it produces the
kind of scores and we just pick the one
that has a high score but basically what
we are telling the machine to do is
produce a score for every category and
then we'll pick the best okay now this
is not possible when the output is
continuous and high-dimensional so the
output is let's say an image we don't
have soft maxes over images okay we
don't have a way of listing all possible
images and then you know normalizing a
distribution over them because it's high
dimensional continuous space even if it
were a really rational continuous space
it would not be possible we will have to
bin that continuous space into discrete
discrete bins and then do a swap max
over that but that doesn't work very
well all right
it only works in small dimension in low
dimension okay so when we have a high
dimensional continuous space we can do
soft max we can't ask the system to give
us a score for all possible outputs
similarly even if it's discrete but
potentially infinite so things like
we're producing text text is
compositional and there is a very very
large number of
of possible text of a given length and
we can't just do a sub snacks over all
possible texts same problem so how do we
how do we represent a distribution or a
bunch of scores over all possible texts
in a compact form
that's where energy based models come in
or probably seek model so that matter
but energy business models in particular
and the solution that energy based
models give us there is the idea that
we're going to use an implicit function
in other words we're gonna we're not
going to a score system to produce a why
we're just going to ask you to tell us
whether an X and a particular Y will
show it are compatible with each other
so it's this text a good translation of
that text okay that sounds kind of weak
right because how are we going to come
up with with that text or machine is
comparing but let's let's hold this hold
this for a bit okay so we're a ninja's
function f of XY is going to take an x
on a wine it's going to tell us if those
two values are compatible with each
other or not okay so if is why a good
label for the image X is y with a good
height high resolution version of the
story low resolution image if Y a good
translation of that sentence in German
etc and so the inference procedure now
is going to be given an X find a Y that
produces a low value for which f of X Y
produces a low value in other words
finally Y that's compatible with X okay
so search over over possible wise for a
value of y that produces a low value for
f of X Y okay so we see idea of
influenced by minimizing some function
and pretty much every model probably
signal probably stick whatever that you
can that people have thought about gonna
work this way I mean except you even
classification multi-class
classification with neural nets or
whatever implicitly worked by energy
minimization by basically finding the
class that has the
the best score which you can think of as
the lowest energy so basically we're
going to try to find an output that
satisfies a bunch of constraints and
those constraints are implemented by
this function f of X Y okay and if
you've heard of graphical models
Bayesian networks you know all that
stuff or even classical AI or Sat
problems they basically they can all be
formulated in those terms as finding the
value of a set of variables that will
mean by some function that measures
their compatibility okay so we're not
talking about running right now okay
we're just talking about inference we're
assuming this function f of X Y is given
to you we're gonna talk about how we
learn it a little later okay so the
energy function is not what we mean by
xoring running it's what we relieve eyes
during inference so inference is
competing Y from X so this energy
function is scalar value it takes small
values when Y is compatible with X and
higher values when Y is not compatible
with X so you'd like this function to
have shape in such a way that for given
X all the values of Y that are
compatible with this X have low energy
and all the values that are not
compatible with that given X have higher
energy and that's all you need because
then the inference procedure is going to
find the Y Y check that written here
which is the value of y that minimizes F
of XY it's not gonna be the value is
gonna be a value because there might be
multiple values okay and your inference
algorithm might actually go through
multiple values or examine multiple
values before kind of giving you one or
several okay let's take an example very
simple example in when dimension of
scalar variable so X here is a is a real
value and Y is a real value and the blue
dots here are data points okay so what
you want is if you want to capture the
dependence
between x and y in the data is that you
would like an energy function that has
either this shape or that shape or some
other shape but which is as a shape that
in such a way that if you take a
particular value of x the value of
weather has a rose value is near the
blue points near the blue dots which are
the data points okay so a function like
this captures the dependency between x
and y now to do the inference of what is
the best y for given X if you have a
function like this you can use gradient
descent so if I give you an X to figure
out what's the best value of y that
corresponds to this X you can start from
some random Y and then back right into
sin find the minimum of the function and
you'll fall down to the boobies here
might be a little harder for this one
but from the point of view of
characterizing the dependency between
those two variables those two energy
functions are just about as good as each
other I come to this the discrete case
when y is discrete is the easy is the
easy case ok and we've already talked
about this and I'll kind of reformulate
this in terms of energy in interested a
couple of minutes ok
so a FIFO model is an explicit function
in that it computes the prediction Y
from from X but it can only make one
prediction we can cheating in the case
of a discrete value but putting out
multiple outputs which correspond to a
skort for every possible classification
but it effect but you can't use this
trick for high dimensional continuous
values or compositional values as as I
said earlier so animation is model is
really an implicit function so remember
you know in calculus for an implicit
function you want the equation of a
circle as a function of x and y you
can't write Y as a function of X you
write an equation that says you know X
square plus y square equal 1 that gives
you the unit circle ok
so XY plus y square equal 1 is I mean s
square plus y square minus 1 isn't it
an implicit function and when you solve
it equal to zero
you get the you get the circle so here's
another example here again scalar values
for x and y and the black dots here are
data points so for the three value of x
indicated by the red bar there's
multiple value of y that are compatible
ones and some of them are actually sort
of continuum of values so we'd like our
energy function to be is something that
looks like this it's basically here I'm
sort of drawing the sort of level level
set of that of that energy function so
it takes low energy on the data points
on higher energy outside this is kind of
a slightly more complicated version of
the module kind of 3d models that I
showed earlier and the question is how
do we train the system so that it adapts
so that the energy function it computes
actually has the proper shape it's nice
when y is continuous that F be smooth
and differentiable so that we can use
gradient based inference algorithms
right so if we have a function like this
and I give you a point X Y you can you
know through gradient descent you can
find the point on the data of any fall
that is closest to it or something
similar to that if I give you a value
for x you can you know search by
gradient descent along the y direction
for a value that kind of minimizes it so
that's the inference algorithm
well sorry an algorithm is really a
prescription then the algorithm is how
you do this minimization and for that
there's all kinds of different methods
gradient based methods are one of them
there are all kinds of methods that are
in the case where F is complicated you
you may not have it may not be possible
to to rely on the search methods so you
may have to use other tricks
in most cases though it simplifies so
just as an aside for those of you who
know a graphical models are a graphical
model is basically an energy based model
where the energy function decomposes as
a sum of energy terms and each energy
turn takes into account a subset of the
variables that you're dealing with so
the beacon of a collection of F's and
some of some FS would take a subset of Y
someone else who take a subset of x and
y's etc and if they organize in a
particular form then there are efficient
inference algorithms to find the minimum
of the sum of those terms with respect
to the variable you're interested in
inferring so this is what you know beef
application and all those algorithms do
for in graphical models this is an aside
you don't if you don't know what I'm
talking about doesn't matter so as I
said the situations where you might want
to use this is when influence basically
is more complex than just you know
running through a few layers of neural
net when the output is high dimensional
and has structure like a sequence or C
or an image or a sequence of images
which is a video when the output has
compositional structure whether it's
text action sequences you know things
like that or when the applet should
resolve from server long chain of
reasoning so it's not just you know I
can just compute the output you need to
kind of solve a constraint satisfaction
problem to basically produce e output or
you know do kind of long chains of
reasoning
okay this is a particular type of energy
based models which is really where where
they start becoming interesting is
energy base model and involve latent
variables okay so so the initiative is
modeled that depends on latent variable
written variable EVM in this case we
depend not just on the variable that you
observe X and the variable Y want to
predict Y but also we depend on some
extra variable Z that nobody tells you
the value of okay and the way you use
this latent variable is is that you
build your model in such a way that the
it depends on the latent variable that
if you use a value of this latent
variable the inference problem would
become easier so let's say you want to
do hang my team recognition and I like
this example which I told you about
already if you know where the characters
are you reading this where it becomes
much easier okay
the main problem here in reading this
word is not just to read the individual
characters but you actually figure out
what the characters are like where where
one character ends well where the other
one begins and if I were to tell you
that it would be much easier for you to
read that to read to read that word if I
were quite good at this so if you if you
read this sequence of characters here in
English if you understand English you
can probably parse it you can probably
figure out where the word boundaries are
because you have this sort of high level
knowledge for whether or you know what
the words are in English I think the
same thing to you inferential you have
no idea what the word boundaries are
okay unless you speak French so
the word batteries in this case and the
character boundaries on top would be
useful to solve the problem it would
allow you for example to in the case of
character recognition to have individual
character recognizers applied to each
character but you don't know where they
are so how do you know how do you solve
that problem so that's that would be a
useful latent variable if I told you
so for speech recognition the problem is
is that you don't know where other
boundaries between the words are you
don't know where the boundaries between
the phonemes are either speech is very
much like like this continuous text
continuous speech we can parse the words
because we know where the words are
because we understand the language but
someone's speaking a language you don't
understand you have a very faint idea
where the word boundaries are most of
the time you can't in languages where
there is no stress in English it's kind
of easy because the stress on the word
so if you can figure out what the stress
is you can probably figure out more or
less where the word boundaries are in
French where there is no stress you
can't have like no way of figuring out
your video now phasma won't say ok
there's only a font where you move right
so you know it's it's kind of a
continuous string of phonemes and it's
very hard to tell where the word
boundaries are unless you know the
language so that would be a useful
relation viable to have because if
someone told you where where those
boundaries were then you will be able to
do the to do the task so that's that's
how you would use latent variables and
this way of using latent variable latent
variables has been used for decades in
the context of speech recognition in the
context of natural language processing
in the context of character recognition
as I said OCR and in a number of
different other applications
particularly ones that involve sequences
but also in computer vision so things
like you know you want to kind of detect
where a person is but you don't know how
that person is is dressed or what what
position that person is in things like
this so you know those are variables
that if you knew that I'm would can I
help you solve the task although
nowadays vision just works okay so if
you have a little variable model this is
how you do inference so you have a new
energy function now it's called not F G
of X Y Z and so in France you're 1703
minimize it with respect to Z and Y okay
so you ask the system give me the
combination of variables of y&z that
mean is this energy function I actually
don't care about the values of Z I only
care about the value of y but I have to
do this simultaneous minimization okay
and I'll give you some more concrete
examples a little later
in fact that's equivalent to defining a
new energy a new energy function f which
I call F infinity here that only depends
on X and y F infinity of X Y is the min
over Z of a of X Y Z you take a function
of X Y Z you find the minimum of this
function over Z Z now gets eliminated
you get a function of x and y ok
in practice you never do that so I
didn't practice to minimize with respect
to Z in y17 history because we don't
know how to represent a function but
there is an alternative to this which is
to define f here with her I write F of
beta or FF index beta of X Y is minus 1
over beta log so I'm or integral over Z
of e to the minus beta e of XYZ now a
little bit of
Titian will you will see that if you
make beta go to infinity this kind of
beta converges to F infinity which is
why I called it F infinity and I went to
this exercise a little earlier in the
class in this integral over Z if beta is
very large the only term that is going
to matter is the term Y of X Y Z de has
the lowest value which is the the one
that has the the lowest value over all
possible values of Z right because all
the other ones are going to be much
bigger because beta is very very large
and so they are that even the
exponential is not going to count
really the only one that's going to
count is the one that has the lowest
value and so if you have only one term
in there which is e of X Y Z for the
value of Z that produces the smallest
value then the log cancels the
exponential and the minus one over beta
can't cancel the minus beta and you're
left with just mean over Z of Z of X Y Z
ok so that's the limit that you see
above so if I define f of X Y in this
way and again then I'm back to the
previous problem of just minimizing F of
XY with respect to Y for doing inference
ok so I think an H and viable model
doesn't make much of a difference you
have an extra minimization with respect
to the latent variable to do but other
than that is fine so there is a big
advantage also to allowing latent
variables which is said by varying the
latent variable over a set I can make
the output the prediction of the system
vary over a set as well so here's a
particular architecture here where X
goes into what I'll call a predictor
which is some sort of neural net it
produces some representation feature
representation of X and then X and Z the
little I will go into
was what I call here decoder which
produces a prediction y-bar okay it's a
prediction for the variable Y that is
the one that we want to predict and our
energy function here just compares Y bar
and y it's simply the distance between
them okay you're familiar with this kind
of diagram we talked about it about them
earlier so if I choose to vary Z over a
set let's say the two dimensional square
here symbolized by this gray diagram
then the the prediction Y bar is going
to vary also over a set in this case
here some sort of ribbon to the mercial
ribbon and what that allows me to do is
basically have a machine now they can
produce multiple outputs okay by varying
the latent variable I can have this
machine produce multiple outputs not
just one that's crucially importance
right
so let's say you're trying to do a video
prediction so there's many ways many
reason why you might want to do video
prediction when one good reason is to
build a very good video compression
compression system for example another
good reason is the video you're trying
to predict is the video you are looking
at from your windshield when you're
driving a car and you'd like to be able
to predict what cars around you are
going to do this is what fray was
working on and so it's very useful to be
able to predict what's going to happen
before before it happens
in fact that's kind of the essence of
intelligence really the ability to
predict now you're looking at me right
now
just a minute you're looking at me right
now I'm talking you're some idea of the
word that is going to come out of my
mouth in a few seconds it's some idea of
what gesture I'm going to do yet some
idea or what direction are going to move
in but not a precise idea right so if
you train your own neural net to make a
single prediction for what I'm gonna
look like two seconds from now there's
no way you can make an accurate
prediction if you train yourself with
least square okay we should train a
comes on that or something to predict
the view of me here Willie square the
best the system can do is produce a
blurry image of me because it doesn't
know if I'm going to move left or right
doesn't know if my hands are going to be
like this or like that and so it's going
to produce the average of all the
possible outcomes and that's gonna be a
blurry image okay so it's very important
that your predictor whatever it is be
able to deal with uncertainty and be
able to make multiple predictions and
the way to parameterize the set of
predictions is through a little variable
and not yet talking about distributions
or probably sick modeling this is this
is way before okay way before we're
talking about this question there see
again
well Susie Zen is not a is not a a
parameter it's not a weight it's a value
that changes for every sample right so
basically during training we haven't
talked about training yet but during
training
I'll give you an X and y you find a Z
that
the energy function with the current
values of the parameters of of those
neural nets okay that's the best yes
your best guess for what the value of Z
is and then you feed that to some loss
function that you're going to minimize
with respect to the parameters of the
network the Ross function is not
necessarily the average not necessarily
the energy it might be something else
okay
in fact most of the time is something
else so in that sense you you run Z you
info Z okay you don't want to use the
term run because learning means you have
one value of the vibe all you you learn
for a whole training set here for Z you
have different value for every sample in
your training set or every time put your
test site for that matter okay so
they're not learned in that sense
they're inferred yeah another example of
this is his translation so translation
has a is a big problem language
translation because there is no single
correct translation of a piece of text
from one language to another usually
there is a lot of different ways to
express the same idea and and why would
you pick one over the other and so it
might be nice if there was some way of
privatizing all the possible
translations that the system could
produce that would correspond to a given
text it's in German that you want to
translate into English there could be
multiple translation you need lists are
all correct and by varying some latent
variable you might you know vary the
translation that is produced okay so now
let's connect this with probabilistic
pricing model there is a way of turning
energies which you can think of as kind
of negative scores if you want because
low energy is good and hydrogen is bad
to turn energies into probabilities and
the way to twenty illusion to
probabilities we talked about this
already
it is to use what's called a Gibbs
Boltzmann distribution so the the form
of this you know goes back to classical
statistical physics in the nineteenth
century and the peer we're given X is
exponential minus beta where beta is
some constant the energy of x and y and
then you want to so that turns all those
energies into positive numbers where we
take the exponential of a number makes
it positive and the minus sign is there
to return low energy into high
probabilities and vice versa
okay and I'm using this convention
because this is what physicists have
been using for the last century more
century and a half
so taking Exponential's you you turn the
energies into positive numbers and then
you normalize so you normalize in such a
way that the the pyx is a properly
normalized distribution over Y and to
make it a properly distribution normal
distribution for y you divide by the
integral or the sum if where it's
discrete over Y of e to the minus beta F
of XY which is the same thing as the top
except you you integrate over all
possible values of Y now if you compute
the integral of this over Y is equal to
one because obviously you get the
integral on top the integral at the
bottom which is a constant and you get
one okay so that confirms that this is
kind of this has this satisfies the
axioms of probability distributions that
it has to be positive numbers that
integrate to one it's a particular like
there's many ways to turn a bunch of
like a function into a function that
integrates to one opposed to a function
in two ways to one what's this one has
interesting properties which are not
going to go through but corresponds to
the so-called maximum entropy
distribution
the beta parameter is kind of arbitrary
it's it's the way you calibrate your
probabilities is as a function of your
energy so the larger the beta the more
sort of binary or at your probability
will be for a given energy function the
beta is very very large is basically
just the the the U of XY that pretty for
the Y that produces the lowest energy
that will have high probability and
everything else will have very low
probability and for small beta for a
small beta then you get kind of a
smoother distribution okay beta in
physics term is a came to an inverse
temperature okay so the beta goes to
infinity is equal to zero temperature
okay a little bit of math it's not that
scary to show you where the formula for
F beta comes from that I talked about
earlier so let's go through this slowly
here the joint probability of P of y and
z given x okay I apply the same bossman
gives Boltzmann distribution formula as
I used before except now it's a joint
distribution over y&z instead of just
the distribution over Y this is for a
latent variable model okay so it's e to
the minus the energy of X Y Z and then I
have to normalize I have to integrate in
the denominator with respect to y and z
so that I get a normalized distribution
over the joint domain of y&z okay so
that's the formula at the top left I can
marginalize in so if I integrate P of y
and z given x I integrate this over Z I
get just P of Y okay that's the
marginalization formula which is at the
top right and so now if I write P of Y X
is simply the integral over Z of the one
at the top left okay which is written
and the second line so at the top we
have integral over zero e to the minus
beta energy of XYZ and at the bottom
integral over y integral over Z of e to
the minus beta e to the X Y Z alright ok
now I'm going to do something very
sneaky no stupid which is that I'm going
to take the log of this formula x minus
1 over beta then x minus beta and then
take the exponential all of those things
cancel out ok the log cancels the
exponential the minus 1 over beta
cancels the minus beta right so I
haven't done anything by doing this e to
the minus beta times minus 1 over beta
log I've done nothing
because everything cancels ok and I do
the same at the bottom and what I see
now is that the stuff in the bracket in
store for me I were previously F beta of
X y equals minus 1 over beta log some
over Z you to go over 0 of e to the
minus beta e of X Y Z and so I can
rewrite this horrible complicated
formula here as e to the minus beta F
theta of X Y divided by integral over Y
of ETA minus beta F of XY what does this
all mean it means that if you have a
latent viable model and you want to
eliminate the Z variable the latent
variable in a probabilistic correct way
you just really find that in the energy
F as this as a function of V or XYZ and
you're done okay you're done is a little
bit of a shortcut because actually
computing this can be very hard ok can
be intractable in fact in most cases
probably it's intractable
I am missing a - in the denominator you
are correct okay so the last few slides
were to say if you have an it enjoyable
that you minimize over inside of your
model or you have a little variable that
you want to marginalize over which is
which you do by defining this new this
energy function f this way
and memorizing corresponds to the
infinite beta limit of this formula it
can be done okay
I mean just to get a substitution in the
second line okay the last two terms in
the second line the bracket are replaced
by F theta of X Y because and I just
defined a bit of X Y this way okay so
just define it this way and if I define
f of X Y this way then P of Y given X is
just an application of the gift awesome
and formula right and Z has been kind of
marginalize implicitly inside of of this
okay so physicists call this a free
energy by the way which is why I call it
f okay so here's the energy and F is a
free energy
so the difference is in prognostic
models you basically don't have the
choice of the objective function you're
gonna minimize and you have to stay true
to the sort of probability for marking
in a sense that every object you
manipulate has to be a normalize
distribution which you may approximate
using variational methods or whatever
here I'm saying ultimately what you want
to make you know what you want to do
with those models is make decisions and
if you're if you're if you build a
system that drives a car and the system
tells you you know I need to turn left
with probably tip on a tour TURN RIGHT
fits for you to point to you're gonna
turn left okay the the fact that the
probabilities there are point two and
point eight doesn't matter what you
wanted to make the decision that is the
the best right because you have to make
a decision you're forced to make a
decision so if you want a system that so
so probabilities are completely useless
if you want to make decisions okay if
you want to combine the output of a
automated system with another one for
example a human or some other system and
this system haven't been trained
together but they've been trained
separately
then what you want is calibrate its
course so that you can combine the
scores of the two systems to make a good
decision and there is only one way to
calibrate scores and is to kind of turn
them into probabilities all other ways
are either inferior or equivalent okay
but if you're gonna train the system
end-to-end to make decisions then then
know then whatever scoring function you
use is fine as long as it gives the best
score to the decision that to the best
decision that gives you way more choices
in how you head all the model where more
choices of how you train it
what objective function you use
basically if you if you insist that your
model be probabilistic you have to do
maximum likelihood so we basically have
to train your model in such a way that
the probability gives to the data you
is maximum okay the problem is that this
is this can only be proven to work in
the case where your model is correct and
your model is never correct in a sense
that you know there's this famous quit
by the famous aesthetician box that said
all models are wrong but some are useful
so probably sick models particularly
artistic models in high dimensional
spaces and probably sick models in
communica minute or old situations like
texts and things like this our
approximate models they're all wrong in
a way and if you try to normalize them
you make them more wrong so you better
off kind of not normalizing them there's
another point that's actually more
important and I come back to this little
diagram and had this one so this is
meant to be an energy function that
captures the dependency between x and y
okay and it's it's like a mountain range
if you want okay
the values are where the black dots are
these are the data points and then
there's kind of mountains all around now
if you try to progress it model with
this imagine that the points are
actually on a thin manifold of of
infinitely an infinitely thin manifold
okay so the the data distribution for
the white dot for the black dots is
actually a just a line okay is one line
to line three lines for their lines they
don't have any any width if you want so
if you're trying to probably sick model
on this you're probably sick model
should give you your density model
should tell you when you are on this
manifold the the outputs should be
infinite the density is infinite and
just actually on that side of it it
should be zero okay that would be the
correct model distribution of the of
this distribution it's a thin plate
not immediately should be infinite but
the integral of it should be one okay
it's very difficult to implement on the
computer not only that is basically
impossible because let's say you want to
compute this function through some sort
of neural net your neural net will have
to have infinite weights and infinite
ways that are calibrated in such a way
that the integral of the output of that
of that system over the entire domain is
1 it's basically impossible you cannot
have accurate probablistic model the
accurate correct probably stick model
for this particular data that I just
told you is impossible this is what
maximum likelihood we want you to
produce and there's no computer in the
world I can compute this okay so in fact
it's not even interesting because
imagine that you had a perfect density
model for the density I just I just
mentioned which is a thin plate in that
XY space you can't do inference if I
give you a value of x and I ask you
where's the best value of y you will be
able to find it because all values of Y
except a set of 0 probability of
probability 0 and it's just you know a
few values like for example for this
value of x there are 3 values that are
possible ok
and there are infinitely now and so he
won't be able to find them there is no
inference algorithm that will allow you
to find them because they're a seraph
they're just derive functions hey how do
you find him so the only way you can
find them is if you make it if you make
your contrast function smooth and
differentiable and then you know you can
start from any point and very gradient
descent you can find a good value for y
for any value of x but this is not
really a good probabilistic model of the
distribution if the distribution is of
the type I mentioned ok so here is a
case where insisting to have a good
politic model actually
is bad ok maximum likelihood sucks so if
you are a true Bayesian you say oh but
like you know you can correct this by I
think of strong prior where the prior
says your density function has to be
smooth and you know you can think of
this as a prior so but everything you're
doing so Bayesian terms take the
logarithm thereof forget about
normalization and you get energy based
models so energy based models that have
a regularizer which is additive to your
energy function a completely equivalent
to Bayesian models where the likelihood
is mixed exponential of the energy and
now you get exponential one term in the
energy you know times exponential
regularizer
and so it's equal to exponential energy
plus regularizer and if you remove the
exponential you have an energy based
model with an additive regularizer
so there is kind of a correspondence
between you know probably seek invasion
methods there but insisting that you do
maximum likelihood is sometimes bad for
you particularly in high dimensional
spaces or community or spaces where your
politic model is very wrong it's not
very wrong in discrete distributions
it's okay
but in that case you know it's really
one and all models are wrong okay so
there is a form of learning and I'll
come back to this to this at length in
future lectures called supervised
running and it's really sort of
encompasses first of all supervised
running but also kind of what people
used to call unsupervised running and a
lot of things and I think it's the
really the future of machine learning is
in sub supervised running and you start
seeing this these days you know over the
last year and a half there's been
enormous progress in NLP because of
systems like Bert and those systems are
trying using sub supervised running a
particular form of stuff super arginine
called denoising auto-encoder which
we'll talk about there's been also quite
a bit of progress over the last three
months or so in
using some supervised learning to train
systems to learn vision systems to learn
features using a you know it's all
supervised pretext tasks and the purpose
of such supervised learning is to train
a system to learn good representations
of the input so that you can
subsequently use those representations
as input to a supervised task or
reinforcement learning task or whatever
the thing is there is a lot more
information that the system can use in
the context of such supervised running
so if you tell you what I mean by itself
supervised learning so sorry poisoning
is that someone gives you a chunk of
data and you're going to train a system
to predict a piece of that data given
another piece of that data okay so for
example I give you a piece of video and
ask you use the first half of the video
and train a model to predict the second
half of that video why would that be
good
why would that be good in the context of
learning features for for vision systems
for example if I trained myself to
predict what the world is going to look
like what my view of this room will look
like if I shave my head a little bit to
the left the best explanation for how to
how the view changes is that every point
in space as a depth as a distance from
our eyes okay
in fact if I sort of inferred somehow
that every point has a distance from I
is then I can very simply explain how
the world changes when I move because
things are closer can have more products
motion than things that are far and you
get this sort of you know perspective
distortion and so
there is this idea somehow that if I
train a system to predict whether what
is going to look like if I move a camera
the system implicitly will run about
depth you will not have you will not
have to be training it to predict depth
in a supervised fashion it will have to
internally kind of discover that there
is such a thing as depth if you wants to
do a good job at that prediction which
means you don't have to hardwired into
the system that the world is
three-dimensional is going to learn this
in minutes by just predicting highs view
of the world changes but you know when
you move the camera now once the system
has figured out that every point has a
depth in the world then the notion that
there are distinct objects that are in
front of the background immediately pops
up because objects are things that move
differently from things are behind okay
there's nothing that pops up immediately
which is the fact that objects that are
now not visible hidden by another one or
still there okay it's just that you
don't see them because they are behind
but this concept that objects still
exist when you don't see them it's not
completely obvious your babies around
this really really early but it's not
clear exactly when because we can
measure that when they are very little
but it probably learned this very quick
once you have identified this concept of
objects perhaps you'll you'll figure out
that a lot of objects in the world
don't move spontaneously okay so there
are inanimate objects and then there are
objects whose trajectories are not
entirely predictable and those are
animate objects or other types of
objects that you know move in not
entirely predictable ways like like you
know the waves in the water on water but
are not animate this is Sally or like
the leaves of a tree and then after a
while you also we you also realize that
objects that
have predictable trajectories generally
don't float in the air if they're not
supported default okay so you you can
start learning about so intuitive
physics about gravity about inertia
babies run this around the age of nine
months so this is not something you're
born with you cannot run this around
nine months you as a baby you run that
gravity is a thing before that you don't
know so the motivation for such
supervised learning and this is one
reason I think such supervised learning
is really the future of machine learning
so in the future of AI is the fact that
animals and humans seem to run an
enormous amount of background knowledge
about the world just by observation by
basically training themselves to predict
so one big question in AI in fact the
question I almost exclusively walk on is
how do we do this
ok we haven't found a complete answer
yet right so I give you a piece of data
it's a video and the machine is going to
pretend there is a piece of that data
that it doesn't see and then another
piece that it season it's going to try
to predict the piece that it doesn't see
from the piece that it sees okay so
pretty future friends in the video
predict missing words in the sentence or
I give you a sentence I block some of
the words and the system trends itself
to predict the words that are missing or
I show you a bunch of a video when I
block you a piece of the frames of some
of the some of the frames piece of the
image for some of the frames you know
predict the less half from the right
half you know right now right now you
only see my right side but even if
you've never seen my left side you could
more or less predict what I look like on
the other side most people are more or
less symmetric except scary Hollywood
characters
so when instance we're so surprised
earning has been unbelievably successful
and it it only happens over the last
year and a half is is text so texts use
a particular type it's a supervised
learning called denoising auto-encoder
so you take a piece of text you remove
some of the words typically ten fifteen
twenty percent of the words so you
replace the the token indicates a word
by basically blank and then you train
some giant and all that to predict the
words that are missing
it's the system cannot make an exact
prediction about which words are missing
and so you train it as a classifier by
producing a big softmax factor for each
word which corresponds to a probability
probability distribution over words okay
and once you've trained this system you
chop off the last layer and you use the
second last layer as a representation of
any text you feed it there's a
particular architecture of this network
that makes it work well but it's
irrelevant to the point that we're
making I'm making right now does
transformer networks that we talked
about last week a little bit so but it's
a reasonable task of completion tasks
filling in the blanks take a sentence
remove some of the words train the
system to predict the words that are
missing that works amazingly well
although type in our pieces stands now
they have the best performance of all
the benchmarks basically are pre-trained
using a method like this and the cool
thing about it is that you know you have
as much text as you want on the web to
pre train those systems you don't need
to label anything is very cheap is very
expensive in terms of computation
because those networks are enormous for
them to work well but it works really
well
so immediately people try to translate
that success into a similar success for
images so let's say I take an image
broke out some pieces of it and then
train some commercial net or something
predict the missing pieces in the image
and the results have been extremely
disappointing doesn't work really I mean
it works well in the sense that the
images get completed with sort of you
know things that make sense but then if
you use the internal representation
learn this way as input to a computer
vision system you can't beat a computer
vision system that has been pre trained
supervised on the image net so what's
the difference
you know why does it work for an LP and
it doesn't work for images and it is the
the difference is that NLP is discrete
or as images or continuous people also
try to do this for video so same idea as
as both accept replaced words by video
frames so here the video to transform a
light system or something similar
remove some of the frames or blocks of
frames and in train the system to
predict the missing frames and the
features you get or not the not-so-great
so that's the the difference is things
seems to work in the discrete world they
don't seem to work in the continuous
world and the reason is because in
discrete in the discrete world we don't
have to represent uncertainty by a big
softmax vector over words in continuous
spaces we don't so if I want to train a
system to do video production I don't
know how to represent a probability
distribution over multiple video frames
um so here's another reason why we might
want to use a supervisor only and deal
with uncertainty and again this is what
her father was working on mothers it's
the fact that we'd like to have we like
our machines to be able to kind of
reason about the world predict what's
going to happen so I told you before an
example where to be able to build a
machine that drives a car you it's
probably good idea to be able to predict
what caused around you are going to do
be able to predict what your car is
going to do if you run you know if
you're driving you're a cliff and you
turn the wheel to the right and you want
to predict in advance that your car is
going to run off the cliff and you don't
you can if you can predict that you're
not gonna do it okay so if you have a
good predictive model of the world the
system that will predict the next state
of the world as a function of the
current state of the world and the
action you take then you can do you can
be you can act intelligently okay well
you need other components to act
intelligently but I'll come back to that
but again this ability to predict is the
essence of intelligence really the fact
that you know some animals are
intelligent is because they really have
a much better model of the world and the
as a consequence are better at acting on
this world - can I get the result they
want so the problem with the world is
that the world is not deterministic or I
mean maybe it is deterministic but we
can't predict exactly what's going to
happen so the fact that is deterministic
or not is irrelevant or will have a
limited capacity or computers have
limited capacity and we can't exactly
predict what's going to what's going to
happen and so we need to be able to
train our system to train our brains to
train our AI systems to predict in the
presence of uncertainty and that's the
most difficult problem that we need to
solve today to make significant progress
in AI how to train the system to make
high dimensional predictions under
uncertainty and here with this
uncertainty
and as I said before probably seek
models are basically gopis okay so let's
take an example with video prediction
here are four frames
what's the continuation of those frames
so it's hard to see that the little girl
is about to grow on her birthday cake
and if you train a neural net with least
square to make predictions so you train
it on thousands of videos of this type
if not millions this is the kind of
prediction you get very blurry why
system cannot predict exactly what's
gonna happen so it predicts the average
of all the possible futures which is the
best way to minimize the squared error
okay and if you want sort of a model
version of this let's say your entire
training set consists of someone putting
a pen on the table and letting it go and
the person always put the pen exactly at
the same place the same way but every
time you do the experiment the pen falls
into you know in a different direction
so basically X is the same for every
training sample but Y is different
because the the pen can fold in any
direction probably with a uniform
distribution so if you try and hour on
that to predict Polly square you'll get
the average of all the possible
predictions which is a transparent pen
you know all around the circle which is
not a good prediction
that's why you need latent variable
models okay so if you make a prediction
by the system but you have latent
variables which indicate what you don't
know about the world
okay so X is what you know about the
well here is the initial segment of the
video of someone putting a pen you know
that when the person gives the figure
the pen will fall but you don't know in
which direction so what you want the
system to tell you is the particular
here that goes from x 2h h to be a
representation
that tells you the penny is going to be
on the on the table but I can tell you
in which direction and then Z will have
the complimentary variable here is the
direction in which the pen actually fell
and then the combination of those two
pieces of information the stuff you can
extract from the observation and stuff
you cannot gives you the prediction Y
bar which hopefully is close to what
actually occurs okay so the way you use
something like this you don't use it for
I mean if you want to use it to kind of
rate a particular scenario you give it X
you give it Y then you ask it what's the
value of the Z variable that minimizes
the prediction error in my model and
then the resulting prediction error is
the energy and it's how you model rate
the compatibility between x and y
you want to predict wise but you have to
do is you observe X and then you kind of
dream up a value of y within a certain
domain and that produces a y bar and
then dream up another value of Z and
that will produce it and produce another
y bar and you can produce a whole set of
Y bars but I kind of draw multiple
values of Z with either set or within
the distribution yes well so if what
you're predicting are the future frames
which observing other the past and
current frame like increasing you mean
increasing the past frames are you
looking at a little bit but you know
after a while things are gonna happen
that really don't depend I mean the
information about what's gonna happen
new future really is not present in the
in the past friends yes so in this
particular case there would be variables
are necessary to make a good prediction
but the information is not present in X
ok so the question was what's the wall
of Z really like you know doesn't
implement a constraint between x and y
or something else and in this particular
example here that i showed the latent
variable
I should several example right one
example I showed is character
recognition if you knew where the
characters are then the task of
recognizing the characters would be
easier and so by making the inference
about where the characters are you know
you sir help you system you have you
build the system in such a way that it
can use that in this particular case
here it's different here the role of the
latent variable is to basically
parameterize the set of possible outputs
that can occur and in the end what you
want is Z to contain
the information about the about why that
is not present in X okay so the
information about you know where I'm
gonna move next I'm going to move left
or right this is not present in anything
you can observe right now it's inside my
brain you can you know you can tell yes
I mean right now here I'm not assuming
anything other than you know pret of X
is a big neural net and decorative
agency is being on that
okay so this is sort of an example of a
visualization of a energy landscape
where we've trained a neural net
basically to compute an energy function
here it's not a neural net it's a very
simple thing actually to capture the
dependency between two variables x and y
and the data points are along this
little spiral here so data points are
kind of sample uniformly along this
spiral and then we train a system to
give you energy to to those points and
and higher energy to everything else now
these two forms there is this is sort of
a conditional but you could call
conditional energy base model which
where there is two sets of viable X&Y
and you're trying to predict Y from X
but it's also another form of energy
based model which are unconditional
there's only a Y no X okay so you're
trying to predict the mutual
dependencies between the various
components of Y the distribution over Y
if you want but there's no X ok so this
is something you won't want to use if
you want to say to image generation
unconditionally right
are you want to just you know model the
mutual dependencies between things but
you don't know which you don't know at
any point if you're going to be able to
observe why why Norway - or none of them
the math is the same really
okay so how are you going to trade those
energy this model this is really where
things become interesting it's the
question of training so training should
do something like the real animation at
the top here it should kind of shape the
energy function because or machine now
is convinced an energy function as a
function of X and why it should shape
the energy function in such a way that
the data points have lower energy than
everything else okay because that's the
way the inference is going to work if if
the correct value of y has really lower
energy than the incorrect values of Y
then or inference algorithm that finds
the value of y that produces the lowest
energy is going to work ok so we need to
shade the energy function so that gives
you energy to the good wise for a given
X and high energy to bad Y's for given X
it goes from our mean it goes from any
domain you want to scaler yes
that is salli so this model actually is
a latent variable model in fact most of
you are probably very familiar with the
energy the model is used here is k-means
so how is this produced okay okay let me
delay this for a bit okay but this is
the energy surface of cdiz which is a
latent variable model let's let's keep
the little viable thing kind of aside
for a minute you know just think of this
as you have an energy f of X Y and the
fact that there may be underlying latent
variable if for now is literally
relevant okay there's two classes of
methods to train energy based models and
again probably seek methods are all kind
of you know special cases within those
one class is called contrasting methods
and this idea is very natural take your
training sample X X over X I Y I and
change the parameters of the energy
function so that its energy goes down
okay easy enough conversely take other
points outside of the manifold of data
so have some process by which you pick
for given X you keep you pick a bad Y
and then push that guy out okay if you
keep doing this with the Rost function
that takes into account those different
different energies then the energy
function is going to take a shape such
that the correct wire will have lower
lower energy than the value wise okay
keep pushing down on the good values of
Y keep pushing up on the dead values of
Y so those are called contrastive
methods and they all differ by how you
pick the Y's that you push up and they
all differ by the last function you use
to
do this pushing up and pushing down
there's a second category of methods and
I'll call them architectural methods in
that case you build the energy function
f of X Y so that the volume of
low-energy regions is limited or is
minimized through regularization so you
build a model in such a way that
whatever you push down on the energy of
data points the rest goes up more or
less automatically because the volume of
cells I can take your energy is limited
or minimized through some regularization
okay those are very broad concepts okay
yes that's one set of techniques but
there's many so there is a set of
methods like score matching for example
that says the gradient of the energy
around the sample should be zero and the
second derivative should be as large as
possible the trace of the Hessian should
be large and so basically you're telling
it you know make the make every data
point a minimum of the energy by making
sure the energy curls up around a
retraining sample it's very very hard to
apply in practice because you have to
compute the gradient with respect to the
waste of the trace of the Hessian of the
energy function with respect to the
inputs that means compute L but yeah for
simple models by touch you can do it
yeah simple models like for linear
models but it's hell I'd stay away from
it okay so there's a number of different
strategies here it says seven strategies
but I can Rev an Isis into those two
categories of contrastive methods and
architectural methods and there are kind
of three sub categories but you know in
contrast even for subcategories in
architectural
and there's some names or voice
algorithms here that you might recognize
some other that you may not recognize
which is okay and I'm gonna try to go
through some of them
now what I need to do it's called score
matching okay bear with me for just one
second
oops
okay so c1 contrastive surg everyone
pushed down the energy of data point
push up everywhere else and this is what
maximum likelihood does and maximum
likelihood pushes down the energy of
data points to minus infinity and pushes
up the energy of other points to plus
infinity which is the problem that we
were just talking about earlier and so
here is what happens so you have this
gift
boss Joint Distribution that gives the
likelihood of Y given X which is for a
particular data point y I X I it gives
you the probability that your model
gives to this particular value of y I
forgiving X I and it's you know
exponential minus beta the energy
divided by exponential minus beta the
energy integrated over all wise okay so
if you want to maximize so let's say
you're a bunch of data points and you
want to maximize so here not writing X
because it doesn't matter and you want
to maximize the poverty your model gives
to this particular value of y you want
to make the energy of this Y small which
means you want to make the e to the
minus beta the energy of this big and
you want to make the stuff at the bottom
as small as possible so instead of
maximizing P of Y we're going to
minimize minus log P of Y okay so minus
log P of Y so if I take the log of this
ratio I'm going to die I'm going to get
the difference of those two terms the
log of the difference you know the
the logs of those two terms the log of
the ratio is the difference of the logs
right so I get log of e to the minus
beta e of Y and then I guess I get minus
log integral over Y you eaten minus beta
Y of Y I did I take the negative of this
because I want to minimize okay so
negative log probability is what I want
to Levis and I get the last function
here at the bottom I divided everything
by beta which makes no difference as far
as the minimum is concerned okay so to
go from the top formula to the bottom
formula you take minus log of the top
formula and you divide by beta
so now we have a that gives us a loss
function and this is our function where
we memorize it says make the energy of
the data point y as low as possible
yi of Y should be small and make the
second term as small as possible which
means which means make the energies that
are inside of this exponential minus as
large as possible so the second term is
going to push up on the energy of every
point including the data point now if I
compute the gradient of this objective
function so this is the poverty stick
approach okay thanks America so compute
the gradient of this jockey function I
get the gradient of the energy at the
data point y okay - this formula here
which is the expected value over Y of
the probability that my model gives to Y
that is given by the gives horsemen
distribution and that is used as a
coefficient to weigh the gradient of the
energy function at that location okay so
this integral here the second term is
basically an expected value of the
gradient I compute the gradient for the
energy function at every point I weigh
every point by the probability that the
model gives to my to that particular Y
and I compute that weighted sum
essentially if Y is discrete this is
discreet some where is continuous is an
integral so the first term so now if I
use this another gradient stochastic
gradient algorithm the first term is
going to try to make the energy of my
data point as well as possible and the
second term is going to push out the
energy of every single point every why
okay
and the problem is can i compute this at
all can i compute this integral so in an
honest chunk of publications in
probabilistic modeling have to do with
how do you either compute this estimate
this or approximate this because that
integral is in interesting cases is
intractable okay if Y is a space of
images I cannot compute an integral over
all possible images there's no way
except if the energy function or the
gradient of the energy function is very
very simple okay most of the time it's
not that simple if you want a complex
model to capture the dependency of the
world it's not going to be that simple
it's gonna be some big neural net so
this an integral is going to be
completely intractable now there is a
huge salvation in the fact that this is
an expected value and so to compute an
approximation and an expected value you
can compute an average of a finite
number of samples so if I sample why
it's from this distribution which is the
distribution of my model gives to Y and
I compute the average of the gradient
over those samples I get some finite
approximation of this it's called Monte
Carlo methods okay it's called a Monte
Carlo approximation invented by
physicists when they were trying to
build a time bomb in the 40s there are
other methods that are based on rational
methods so I don't really know how to
compute P I can't compute the city world
but let's say I replace K by another
distribution Q for which I can't compute
this average let's say Gaussian or
something and then I try to make you as
close to P as possible that's called
variational methods okay you probably
heard that term anytime
that's a basic idea variational methods
you approximate an expectation over a
distribution by replacing the
distribution by something you can
actually compute and you try to make
this computable distribution as close as
possible to the real distribution using
some measure KL divergence right so
here's came in so k-means is a you can
think of k-means as a energy based model
energy based model you can interpret
candies in terms of energy of this model
is anyone okay with what Keynes is or
you forgotten we can use this
okay so k-means is this very simple
clustering algorithm where the energy
function if you've never heard of it
this is a way to explain he means the
energy function is written at the top
here ye of Y Z is y minus W Z where W is
a matrix and Z is a set of one hot
vectors okay so see this discrete
variable with K possible values and it's
a K dimensional vector with one
component equal to 1 and all the other
ones equal to 0 ok so you multiply Z by
the matrix W the effect is that what you
get as this product is one of the
columns of W ok the kernel W that gets
multiplied by the component of Z that's
equal to 1
yes we produced and everything else is
is gone ok so that product selects one
column from the beam the columns of W
are called prototypes ok
and if I give you a Y the way you do
inference is that you figure out which Z
which of the K possible vectors of Z
minimizes the reconstruction error
realizes the squared distance between
the corresponding column of W and the
data point that I'm looking at and the
energy is just is quite distance between
the two ok now the energy function you
see here represented in this chart you
right here what you see here are kind of
black blobs and those correspond to
quadratic wells around each of the
prototypes of W so the system he has
been trained and he placed the columns
of W along the manifold of training
samples which is this spiral that's
where all the training samples are
selected and the way this is trained is
very simple you just memorize the
expected the average energy over a
training set okay so basically I give
you why why is a training sample you
find a Z that minimizes the energy so
you find the prototype that is closest
to Y the comma W that's closest to Y and
then they do one step of gradient
descent so you move that vector close to
Y closer to Y then you take another Y
select which columns of W is closest to
it and move that column little bit
closer to Y then you keep doing this
that's not exactly the KB's algorithm
this is the kind of stochastic gradient
form of the k-means algorithm the real
k-means algorithm actually kind of does
sort of coordinate descent if you want
so it fails both with the entire
training set and figures out for each
data point which column of W is closest
to it and then after you've done this
you compute every data point every
corner W as the average of all the data
points to which is associated and it
goes a bit faster if you do it this way
as opposed to stochastic gradient but
the result of the same in the end you
minimize the average of the energy over
the training set okay so that's an
example if there was a question of a
latent variable earlier that's an
example of a latent variable model very
simple one where the decoder is linear
is no dependency on X and what you're
just trying to do is model the
distribution over Y okay here y is
two-dimensional and you're just trying
to say you know if I do one value of y
can you tell me if I knew why one can
you tell me anything about the way you
y2 and once you have this energy
function you can I give you y one you
can predict what the value of y two
should be I give you a random point you
can tell me what's the closest point on
the day of any fold by just searching
for the closest prototype basically okay
so he means that just explained here
belongs to the architectural methods
it's not a contrasting methods as you
can observe I did not push up on the
energy of anything I just push down on
the energy of stuff the k-means is built
in such a way that there is only K
points in the space that can have zero
energy and everything else will have
higher energy okay it's just designed
this way right so it's architectural in
that sense once I've decided on K have
limited the volume of space in a in Y
they can take low energy because there's
only K points that can have zero energy
everything else grows quadratically as I
move away from them now let's talk about
if there's a bunch of other methods
these are my favorite methods I think
ultimately everybody will be using
architectural methods but right now the
stuff that works in images is
contrastive per se okay so contrastive
methods I have data points and
my model computes an energy function
let's say that looks like this so I'm
cool I'm drawing the contours of equal
cost okay it's like a topographic map
so obviously that model is bad right
because it gives you energy to those
points here right those points have low
energy and they should not and then
those points have high energy and they
should not so what should I do
so obviously if I take if I take a a
training sample here and I change the
parameters of F F of an X Y so that the
energy goes down it's really going to
move the the function to have Canha
lower values in that region but that may
not be sufficient because it could be
that my energy function is permit rise
in such a way that it could be flat
could be zero everywhere so I need to
explicitly push up on other places okay
and so a good a good location to push up
would be those red locations here these
are locations that my model gives you
energy to but should not have low energy
okay so let's say let's say this is my
training sample right now okay the the
big black dot here that's my training
sample one way I can try to contrastive
system is by saying I'm going to push
down on the energy of that point and I'm
going to retrieve that point a little
bit by corrupting it some way adding
noise to it and we will push up on the
energy of a point that's near body okay
and I'm going to do some multiple times
this sufficiently many times eventually
the energy function is going to curl up
around every sample because I modify the
sample and I push up you know I corrupt
it a little bit and I push up on the
energy of that corrected sample the
contrastive sample so eventually the
energy is going to take the right pace
something a little smarter instead of
sort of randomly perturbing the this
Trini sample by you know some
perturbation around it I'm going to use
gradient descent to kind of go down in
the energy surface and then I'm going to
get this point and push it up okay that
makes more sense right because I'm going
for the jiggler here I you know the
system can finds the point that the
system gives that it gives her energy to
currently and it pushes up right so the
procedure is here is a training sample
move down in the energy surface you'll
find a value of y that has lower energy
than the one you started from and then
that's the contracted sample push it up
push down on the original sample push up
on this new sample you just got now this
might be expensive and your energy
function may be complicated may have
local minima so here's another technique
the other technique is start from the
same training sample and imagine that
this surface is like is like a you know
like your smooth mountain range and then
give a random kick to the to this marble
think of it as a marble you're going to
give it a random kick in a random
direction and you're going to simulate
this as a marble rolling down this
energy surface so let's say I'm going to
kick it in this direction it's going to
go in this direction for a while and
then it's going to go down and the
energy after a while cut it off
you get a point at the end of this
church actually push it up okay so I'm
doing this very informally but in fact
there are so depending on how you do
this here I'm explaining the principles
of how those methods work but in fact if
you are interested in producing modeling
and what you're interested in is doing
maximum likelihood what you need to do
is send sample produce samples according
to the probability your model gives to
the same thing the samples and there's
ways to run those algorithms in such a
way that the ratio of the probability
with which you will you will pick two
samples corresponds to the ratio of
their probabilities in the given by the
model which is all you need and that's
essentially done by you know the details
of how you implement those kind of
trajectories basically and like the
noise that you used to so okay so did he
give you names for this okay the the
random noise e corresponds to an
algorithm called denoising auto-encoder
and Fredo is going to tell you more
about this the the gradient descent and
random kick versions the random kick
that's called
contrastive divergence and their form of
this for and if you do a search through
the space by kind of random perturbation
sort of trying to find low-energy space
with noise it's a special case of Monte
Carlo methods and if it's a continuous
trajectory or not a continuous but if
it's a trajectory could be discrete it's
called Markov chain Monte Carlo methods
or
CMC and if it's in a continuous space
where you use kind of this rolling ball
with a random kick method that's called
Hamiltonian Monte Carlo agency there's a
question no okay where the time you let
me just talk about denoising
auto-encoder so what's the Dinos in
go-to encoder it's a particular type of
energy based model where you start with
a Y so that you only have Y's go so you
start with why you corrupt it
so this is the little diagram that I
showed earlier you correct this sample
okay you get another sample that I I'm
not gonna call and you pass this through
an encoder which is a neural net and a
decoder which is another neural net and
then you compare the output which is a
reconstruction for Y with Y this is just
in the classical form this is the
distance between y and y bar squared
okay
and you see here in the network on the
left is just some some neural net that
you train the corruption is built by
hand
okay it's not trained so what does that
do for you this actually pushes up the
energy of corrupted points okay so here
the energy is so this is how you train
the system but the actual system doesn't
have the corruption you give it a why
you run it through the encoder and the
decoder and measure the reconstruction
error okay so it's exactly the same
diagram except no corruption so the
corruption is for training and this is
how you use it okay what does that do
for you you have space of Y you have
data points take a point Y and corrupt
it
okay and now you train this new on that
this encoder/decoder to basically
reconstruct this corrupted point - from
the corrupted point to produce the
original point the original training
point okay so the the neural net
function is going to map it's going to
map this point to that point okay what
does that mean that means when you when
you plug a vector here why and you do
this for every training sample and a
large number of corruptions okay well
that means is that when you plug a a
point Y here on the input and you
measure its energy which is a
reconstruction error this point if it's
on the manifold if it's on the menu full
of data is going to be reconstructed as
itself therefore its energy here which
is a reconstruction air will be zero
okay if he's trained properly whereas if
you put on the input a point that is
outside the manifold it's going to get
reconstructed as the closest point on
the manifold because it's been trying to
do that therefore the reconstruction
error here will be that this will be
this distance okay well that means is
now that the energy computed by this
delusion go to an encoder it's such that
it grows quadratically as you move away
from the manifold of data if the thing
is properly trained okay so that's an
example of contrastive methods because
you you say all the manifold things
should be zero the reconstruction energy
should be zero
outside the manifold the reconstruction
energy should be the distance to the
medical okay
this is big so bird is trained this way
except the space is discrete
they'll come in at Oriel because it's
text and the corruption technique
consists in masking some of the some of
the words and then the reconstruction
consists in predicting the words are
missing
you can always copy the words that are
not missing so you don't need to do it
okay
so it's a special case of you as you go
to encoder it's actually called a masked
rotary encoder because the type of
corruption you do is masking pieces of
the input okay all right out of time
we'll talk about more of those
techniques next time